Collection Guide to the Nathan H. Hill Papers, 1810-1950
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Nathan Hill papers 1810-1950
Hill, Nathan H.
1.2 linear feet
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Nathan H. Hill was a teacher in Lincolnton (Lincoln Co.), N.C. Collection includes letters to Nathan H. Hill concerning his work teaching freedmen in Lincolnton, N.C., including letters from Albion W. Tourgée. The collection also consists of letters from family members and others, receipts, material related to Guilford College, and several items about the Quakers' work with African Americans after the Civil War.
hillnathan
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Nathan Hill Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1959.
Biographical Note
Teacher in Lincolnton (Lincoln Co.), N.C.
Collection Overview
Collection contains chiefly correspondence, dates ranging 1830-1950, to and from Nathan H. Hill concerning his work teaching freedmen in Lincolnton, N.C., as well as family correspondence and other documentation from members of the Hill, Usher, Wright, Jones, Self, Bostick, and Thornburg families and their friends and associates. Family correspondence relates to routine family matters and everyday life. Of particular interest are several letters from Albion W. Tourgée, founder of the Bennett College, a historically black college for women in Greensboro, N.C. In these letters, Tourgée discusses conditions of former plantation lands in the South and states that he will encourage people from the North to purchase these lands. Nathan Hill also received frequent correspondence from George Dixon, a Quaker from Yorkshire, England who was also involved with the freedmen's schools in North Carolina. These letters, bulk dates ranging 1865-1867, describe the Quakers' work with African-Americans after the Civil War, especially the freedmen's school in Lincolnton, N.C.
The papers also include legal documents, dates ranging from 1810-1927, and financial documents, dates ranging 1823-1915, as well as some undated documents. The materials consist primarily of bills receipts, letters granting power of attorney, letters of indenture, statements of debt repayment, insurance paperwork, vouchers for property rental, and other materials relating to property, debts, and other public concerns, primarily in Randolph County, N.C.
There are a small number of bound materials such as a grade school register, voter registries, and an undated day book. The collection also contains printed materials relating to church activities and Guilford College.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Hill, Nathan H.; Tourgée, Albion Winegar, 1838-1905; Guilford College; Freedmen -- Education -- North Carolina; Freedmen -- North Carolina -- Lincolnton; Quakers -- North Carolina; Reconstruction -- North Carolina; Lincolnton (N.C.)-- History
Contents of Collection
- Nathan H. Hill papers
  - Correspondence, 1830 January 16-1868 January 9 (Box 1)
    This folder contains correspondence chiefly concerning Nathan H. Hill and his work in the freedmen's school in Lincolnton, N.C.
  - Correspondence, 1868 May 3-1872 April 28 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1872 June 29-1889 December 9 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1890 February 12-1893 November 21 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1894 January 1-1897 December 6 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1898 March 27-1899 December 29 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1900 January 9-1904 February 14 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1904 March 13-1905 December 21 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1906 February 7-1909 May 20 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1909 July 13-1950 May 6 (Box 1)
  - Legal Documents, 1810 July 1-1868 March 27 (Box 2)
    This folder contains legal documentation concerning power of attorney, letters of indenture, debt repayment, insurance, and vouchers for the rental of a Freedmen's School building in North Carolina. Many of the documents within pertain to issues in Randolph County, N.C. Of note, this folder contains a letter of indenture for a seven year old Negro boy.
  - Legal Documents, 1868 May 15-1877 October 31 (Box 2)
  - Legal Documents, 1879 September 1-1927 May 1 (Box 2)
  - Financial Documents, 1823-1853 (Box 2)
  - Financial Documents, 1854-1869 (Box 2)
  - Financial Documents, 1870-1915 (Box 2)
  - Financial Documents, undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 2)
    Contains five folders of undated correspondence and other writings and materials concerning property ownership, cotton prices, and financial documentation such as receipts and informal documentation of debt acknowledgment.
  - Day Book, undated (1850s-1860s?) (Box 3)
  - Registry of Voters, 1867 August 21-22 (Box 3)
  - Registry of Voters, 1867 September 4-5 (Box 3)
  - White's Graded School Register, 1872 September 18-1872 December 20 (Box 3)
  - Printed Materials, 1845-1901 (Box 3)
    Contains two folders of printed materials relating to Guilford College and church-related activities such as annual meeetings, missionary work, and Sunday school. Includes materials from Sandy Creek Baptist in Chatham County, N.C., the Christian Advocate, and the United Society of Christian Endeavor.